<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes" ?>
<!DOCTYPE bugzilla SYSTEM "https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/bugzilla.dtd">

<bugzilla version="3.2.5.1-2"
          urlbase="https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/"
          maintainer="Dave McMurtrie &lt;dave64@andrew.cmu.edu&gt;"
>

    <bug>
          <bug_id>1273</bug_id>
          
          <creation_ts>2002-06-19 10:01 EDT</creation_ts>
          <short_desc>quote characters in envelope structure are not properly escaped?</short_desc>
          <delta_ts>2010-10-18 12:42:57 EDT</delta_ts>
          <reporter_accessible>1</reporter_accessible>
          <cclist_accessible>1</cclist_accessible>
          <classification_id>1</classification_id>
          <classification>Unclassified</classification>
          <product>Cyrus IMAP</product>
          <component>IMAP</component>
          <version>2.0.x</version>
          <rep_platform>PC</rep_platform>
          <op_sys>Linux</op_sys>
          <bug_status>CLOSED</bug_status>
          <resolution>INVALID</resolution>
          
          
          
          
          <priority>P2</priority>
          <bug_severity>bug</bug_severity>
          <target_milestone>Future</target_milestone>
          
          
          
          <everconfirmed>1</everconfirmed>
          <reporter name="Marc Groot Koerkamp">marc@its-projects.nl</reporter>
          <assigned_to name="Larry Greenfield">leg+cyrus@andrew.cmu.edu</assigned_to>
          
          

      

      

      
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Marc Groot Koerkamp">marc@its-projects.nl</who>
            <bug_when>2002-06-19 10:01:46 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>I&apos;m not sure if this is the responsability of the imapserver but anyway it 
would help if the subject returned in an envelope structure as part of a 
bodystructure escaped the quote characters.

Without this I can&apos;t properly proces the returned bodystructure.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Larry Greenfield">leg+cyrus@andrew.cmu.edu</who>
            <bug_when>2002-06-19 10:38:35 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>huh? can you attach a protocol log showing the problem? Cyrus will usually
decide to send strings with &quot; or ) as literals to the client, avoiding any
quoting issues.

with very few exceptions, IMAP allows any string to be sent as either an atom, a
quoted string, or a literal and applications must be prepared to deal with any
of them.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Marc Groot Koerkamp">marc@its-projects.nl</who>
            <bug_when>2002-06-19 15:52:16 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Uhh protocol log?
Cyrus works well but when I want to parse the bodystructure with php 4.1.2 into 
a messageclass then I look quoted strings and make exceptions for escaped 
quotes. (squirrelmail i&apos;m talking about)
If for example I have a message with a message/rfc822 attached then the 
bodystructure contains the envelope structure. If there is a subject like:
test &quot; )
then things goes wrong. As I understood from the RFC&apos;s the qoute in the subject 
string should be escaped so the imapclient can skip the \&quot; in de returned 
bodystructure.
If don&apos;t know how I can verify if cyrus does this correctly.

I asked other people to test this with other imap-servers and they have no 
problems. That was the reason I thought it might be a cyrus problem.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Larry Greenfield">leg+cyrus@andrew.cmu.edu</who>
            <bug_when>2002-06-19 16:12:50 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Protocol log: a transcript of the exact communication from the server to the client.

If you can&apos;t show me exactly a response which you think is wrong, I can&apos;t fix
it.  I&apos;ve verified that the server correctly returns a response for a Subject like
test &quot; )</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Marc Groot Koerkamp">marc@its-projects.nl</who>
            <bug_when>2002-06-20 07:43:01 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>OK, thanx for the response. Cyrus returned the subject in the regarding 
envelope structure as a literal. The function used in squirelmail didn&apos;t look 
for literals :-(

I will close the bug</thetext>
          </long_desc>
      
      

    </bug>

</bugzilla>