<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes" ?>
<!DOCTYPE bugzilla SYSTEM "https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/bugzilla.dtd">

<bugzilla version="3.2.5.1-2"
          urlbase="https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/"
          maintainer="Dave McMurtrie &lt;dave64@andrew.cmu.edu&gt;"
>

    <bug>
          <bug_id>2641</bug_id>
          
          <creation_ts>2005-03-31 22:37 EDT</creation_ts>
          <short_desc>Squatter Causes Kernel Crash! Confirmed across hardware and OSes!</short_desc>
          <delta_ts>2010-10-19 07:42:22 EDT</delta_ts>
          <reporter_accessible>1</reporter_accessible>
          <cclist_accessible>1</cclist_accessible>
          <classification_id>1</classification_id>
          <classification>Unclassified</classification>
          <product>Cyrus IMAP</product>
          <component>IMAP</component>
          <version>2.2.x</version>
          <rep_platform>Other</rep_platform>
          <op_sys>Linux</op_sys>
          <bug_status>CLOSED</bug_status>
          <resolution>DEFERRED</resolution>
          
          
          
          
          <priority>P5</priority>
          <bug_severity>bug</bug_severity>
          <target_milestone>2.3.17</target_milestone>
          
          
          
          <everconfirmed>1</everconfirmed>
          <reporter name="Lee Hoffman">lee@disinfo.com</reporter>
          <assigned_to name="Ken Murchison">murch@andrew.cmu.edu</assigned_to>
          <cc>joost_cyrus@antarean.org</cc>
          <qa_contact name="The Cyrus Bugzilla List">cyrus-bugzilla@lists.andrew.cmu.edu</qa_contact>

      

      

      
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Lee Hoffman">lee@disinfo.com</who>
            <bug_when>2005-03-31 22:37:19 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>We had cyrus 2.2.12 running on Redhat 9.0 for some time, and scheduled squatter
to run nightly. Once every month or two the box would mysteriously crash. When
it crashed, the box would still be pingable, and you could telnet to various
ports, but no services actually responded. All log entries stop the moment the
kernel crashes. The only solution is a physical reboot.

Anyway we assumed this was a problem with cyrus and RH 9 or the hardware it was
running on. Well we have now switched over to a completely new server (brand new
poweredge 2650) and are running a completely different OS (gentoo with the
latest kernel) and the problem still exists. 

We&apos;ve moved teh cronjob that runs squatter to different times of the day, and
sure enough within 1-2 hours of squatter running (always while its still
running) the server is crashing in the same way.

Obviously this is a critically serious bug. Squatter doesnt seem to be dieing on
any particular user or message (atleast according to the last indexing user/...
 in the logs).</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Derrick">shadow@andrew.cmu.edu</who>
            <bug_when>2005-03-31 23:02:29 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Different versions of Linux isn&apos;t exactly &quot;across OSes&quot;, if the Linux kernel has a bug, the Linux kernel has a 
bug. As squatter is a user process and does not involve a loadable kernel module, if you&apos;re encountering a 
kernel bug, the kernel bug is going to need to be fixed. If you cannot pursue it with your Linux vendor, I 
suggest applying a patch to provide a kernel debugger such as kgdb or kdb and when the machine is 
hung, dropping to the debugger and seeing what&apos;s happening. If this is too severe, perhaps you could 
start by attaching a console to the machine and forcing it to not blank, to see if any messages appear on 
the console before the machine stops responding that would give you a hint as to why it&apos;s gone. </thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Roeleveld">joost_cyrus@antarean.org</who>
            <bug_when>2010-10-19 07:41:29 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>http://www.cyrusimap.org/mediawiki/index.php/Bugzilla_Cleanup_Guidelines

I am using squatter in a cron-job on a nightly basis on Gentoo.
Currently running 2.3.14 and have never had this cause a crash on my system.
Not sure which version I used first, but I have been using Cyrus succesfully for the past 4 or 5 years without ever seeing this issue.

As the person originally reporting this issue has not responded to a request for further tracing, I have closed this bug.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
      
      

    </bug>

</bugzilla>