<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes" ?>
<!DOCTYPE bugzilla SYSTEM "https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/bugzilla.dtd">

<bugzilla version="3.2.5.1-2"
          urlbase="https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/"
          maintainer="Dave McMurtrie &lt;dave64@andrew.cmu.edu&gt;"
>

    <bug>
          <bug_id>2643</bug_id>
          
          <creation_ts>2005-04-04 16:03 EDT</creation_ts>
          <short_desc>altnamespace shows mailboxes twice</short_desc>
          <delta_ts>2005-10-25 11:50:39 EDT</delta_ts>
          <reporter_accessible>1</reporter_accessible>
          <cclist_accessible>1</cclist_accessible>
          <classification_id>1</classification_id>
          <classification>Unclassified</classification>
          <product>Cyrus IMAP</product>
          <component>IMAP</component>
          <version>2.3.x</version>
          <rep_platform>All</rep_platform>
          <op_sys>All</op_sys>
          <bug_status>NEW</bug_status>
          
          
          
          
          
          <priority>P2</priority>
          <bug_severity>bug</bug_severity>
          <target_milestone>Future</target_milestone>
          
          
          
          <everconfirmed>1</everconfirmed>
          <reporter name="Joseph Brennan">brennan@columbia.edu</reporter>
          <assigned_to name="Ken Murchison">murch@andrew.cmu.edu</assigned_to>
          <cc>ken@oceana.com</cc>
          <qa_contact name="The Cyrus Bugzilla List">cyrus-bugzilla@lists.andrew.cmu.edu</qa_contact>

      

      

      
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Joseph Brennan">brennan@columbia.edu</who>
            <bug_when>2005-04-04 16:03:10 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Using:
altnamespace: true
unixhierarchysep: true

We get as expected three namespaces:

b NAMESPACE
* NAMESPACE ((&quot;&quot; &quot;/&quot;)) ((&quot;Other Users/&quot; &quot;/&quot;)) ((&quot;Shared Folders/&quot; &quot;/&quot;))


But the Other Users and Shared Folders namespaces appear among a user&apos;s own folders too:

d LIST &quot;&quot; &quot;%&quot;
* LIST (\Noinferiors) &quot;/&quot; &quot;INBOX&quot;
* LIST (\HasChildren) &quot;/&quot; &quot;mailbox2&quot;
* LIST (\Noselect \HasChildren) &quot;/&quot; &quot;Other Users&quot;
* LIST (\Noselect \HasChildren) &quot;/&quot; &quot;Shared Folders&quot;
d OK Completed (0.000 secs 10 calls)

Listing Other Users and Shared Folders twice is a bug.  This is never correct.

The solution I propose is that in altnamespace, any LIST &quot;&quot; &quot;*&quot; or LIST &quot;&quot; &quot;%&quot; command return only the 
user&apos;s own mailboxes (translate &quot;&quot; to &quot;INBOX.&quot; internally).

If there is demand, there might be an alternative altnamespace where NAMESPACE returns only one
namespace, namely &quot;&quot;, and then LIST &quot;&quot; would work as shown above.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Derrick">shadow@andrew.cmu.edu</who>
            <bug_when>2005-04-13 12:11:11 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Ken, care to comment on this? 

Also, thoughts on doing it:
* NAMESPACE ((&quot;INBOX.&quot; &quot;.&quot;)) ((&quot;Other Users/&quot; &quot;/&quot;)) ((&quot;Shared Folders/&quot; &quot;/&quot;))</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Joseph Brennan">brennan@columbia.edu</who>
            <bug_when>2005-04-13 12:25:23 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Interestingly some clients do not list Other Users and Shared Folders twice, as if they do some routine 
to identify duplicates and suppress them.  Nice client behavior.  It really sticks out as bad with 
Mulberry.

I take it that some solution is wanted where LIST &quot;&quot; &quot;%&quot; will in fact show all mailboxes, so that non-
namespace clients like Outlook and Outlook Express can see all mailboxes.  I think this can be allowed 
without making any of the three namespaces be &quot;&quot;.

I don&apos;t know what prior discussion has taken place on this question.  I cannot find much.  Possibly the 
clients suppressing duplication makes it less of an issue than it seemed.  
</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Derrick">shadow@andrew.cmu.edu</who>
            <bug_when>2005-04-13 12:29:08 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Well, the problem I have is much of the discussion on this took place 2 Cyrus maintainers ago.
Anyway, 
&gt;I take it that some solution is wanted where LIST &quot;&quot; &quot;%&quot; will in fact show all mailboxes
Well, not necessarily, it just seems horribly wrong to secretly rewrite things out from under the user if we 
can avoid doing so, and the &quot;INBOX.&quot; &quot;.&quot; approach would seem to be cleaner in that respect.
</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Ken Murchison">ken@oceana.com</who>
            <bug_when>2005-04-13 12:49:26 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Why change the separator for the INBOX namespace?  This would prevent the user
from using &apos;.&apos; in their personal mailboxes, while allowing it for public mailboxes.

I&apos;m fairly confident that this worked correctly when I first wrote the code, and
we (I?) broke it while fixing the stupid %* or *% problem (or whatever it was).</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Ken Murchison">ken@oceana.com</who>
            <bug_when>2005-04-13 13:07:11 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Actually, I should have read the original post more clearly?  Where is the
duplicate listing?  AFAICT, NAMESPACE and LIST &quot;&quot; &quot;%&quot; work as expected.  The
output is really no different with altnamespace disabled, just the &quot;personal&quot;
and &quot;shared&quot; namespaces are swapped.  Its always possible that I&apos;m
misunderstanding the problem, btu I think Cyrus&apos; output is correct.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Derrick">shadow@andrew.cmu.edu</who>
            <bug_when>2005-04-13 13:09:37 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Er, because I have &quot;.&quot; on the brain.  &quot;INBOX/&quot; &quot;/&quot; 
</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Joseph Brennan">brennan@columbia.edu</who>
            <bug_when>2005-04-13 13:44:21 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>RFC 2342 defines three possible namespaces as Personal, Other Users, Shared Folders.  The many 
examples do not show any of the three as including the other two.  That&apos;s the bug.

I now think it would work well if NAMESPACE named INBOX/, Other Users/, and Shared Folders/, so that 
clients using namespace would have those three as roots; and then also, clients not using namespace 
and searching &quot;%&quot; or &quot;*&quot; would see all mailboxes in one list.  So, if I use namespace, I might do LIST &quot;&quot; 
&quot;INBOX.%&quot;, and if I don&apos;t use namespace, I might do LIST &quot;&quot; &quot;%&quot;, see INBOX. in the response, and then do 
LIST &quot;&quot; &quot;INBOX.&quot;.  So it works with or without namespace.
</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Ken Murchison">ken@oceana.com</who>
            <bug_when>2005-04-13 13:58:50 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Ah, OK, I see your complaint.  The problem is that there is no way via ther LIST
command to isolate a namespace which has an empty (&quot;&quot;) prefix (which is the case
with personal mailboxes in altnamespace).  You have the same problem when
altnamespace is disabled -- you can&apos;t LIST just shared mailboxes without also
listing personal and other users.  Regardless of the altnamespace setting, LIST
&quot;&quot; &quot;%&quot; is going to list the toplevel of all mailboxes hanging off of the &quot;root&quot;,
which includes the namespace prefixes.  The only way to have personal mailboxes
appear at the toplevel is to leave things the way they are, with an empty prefix
for personal folders.  Given the fact that I was contracted to write the
altnamespace with exactly this in mind, I&apos;m reluctant to change this code.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Henrique de Moraes Holschuh">hmh@debian.org</who>
            <bug_when>2005-04-13 14:18:24 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>I agree with Ken.  The current mode works very well, even if it is not perfect.
 I would be wary of touching it.

OTOH, we COULD add a third mode where there are the three separate namespaces
INBOX/ Shared Folders/ Other Users/ (or INBOX. Shared Folders. Other Users.
depending on the hierarchy separator).

That would give us the best of all three worlds, wouldn&apos;t it?  Is that viable?</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Derrick">shadow@andrew.cmu.edu</who>
            <bug_when>2005-04-13 14:25:53 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>&gt;OTOH, we COULD add a third mode where there are the three separate namespaces

RFC2342 says
5. NAMESPACE Command

   Arguments: none

   Response:  an untagged NAMESPACE response that contains the prefix
                 and hierarchy delimiter to the server&apos;s Personal
                 Namespace(s), Other Users&apos; Namespace(s), and Shared
                 Namespace(s) that the server wishes to expose. 

Ok, so my question is, why is &quot;&quot; a personal namespace, as opposed to &quot;INBOX/&quot;? Is this a case where I&apos;m 
missing intent?</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Derrick">shadow@andrew.cmu.edu</who>
            <bug_when>2005-04-13 14:29:05 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Talked with Ken offline, he poked me and I realized where I had the disconnect: having the personal 
mailboxes at the top level means the personal namespace is (well, becomes) &quot;&quot;. So then a third mode that 
can be enabled and which behaves differently in this case is probably useful.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Joseph Brennan">brennan@columbia.edu</who>
            <bug_when>2005-04-13 14:30:21 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Right, 2342 calls for three prefixes.  I agree that LIST no prefix should list everything.
</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Ken Murchison">ken@oceana.com</who>
            <bug_when>2005-04-13 14:34:35 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Good luck to whoever decides to dig back into the LIST code to do this!  Be
forwarned that it takes a lot more time, beer, and patience than you would
think.  :)  Although it might be easier than when I had to do altnamespace and
virtdomains from the ground up.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Ken Murchison">ken@oceana.com</who>
            <bug_when>2005-04-13 14:42:27 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Back to the Mulberry problem.  Has anyone discussed this with Cyrus Daboo?  I&apos;m
surprised that he doesn&apos;t handle altnamespace properly.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Joseph Brennan">brennan@columbia.edu</who>
            <bug_when>2005-04-13 15:22:12 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>I asked on the Mulberry mailing list, to silence.  But Mulberry does correctly show what the server says 
are the three namespaces.

Compare to a response from U Wash:
NAMESPACE ((&quot;&quot; &quot;/&quot;)) NIL ((&quot;#shared/&quot; &quot;/&quot;))
Here we have a no-prefix namespace for personal, but listing no-prefix does not include #shared/.
(I might be hurting my case showing another no-prefix namespace response!)

</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Ken Murchison">ken@oceana.com</who>
            <bug_when>2005-04-13 15:31:39 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Hmm, that is contrary to what I would expect, but I know some of the older CMU
guys never liked UW&apos;s &quot;special&quot; #whatever prefixes.  FWIW, an Exchange server
(which is what altnamespace was/is designed to emulate, does:

* NAMESPACE ((&quot;&quot; &quot;/&quot;)) NIL ((&quot;Public Folders/&quot; &quot;/&quot;)) 

I wonder what a LIST &quot;&quot; %  on Exchange displays?</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Joseph Brennan">brennan@columbia.edu</who>
            <bug_when>2005-04-14 11:30:54 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>We tested clients with altnamespace.  Netscape 7 and Apple Mail use namespace but suppress the 
duplication.  Outlook, Outlook Express, Pine and IMP do not use namespace.  So the only client left that 
we care about is Mulberry, and since we control the distribution under our license we could distribute it 
to show only Personal namespace (which shows everything!).

I&apos;ll get this to Cyrus Daboo.  I wouldn&apos;t argue too far since Mulberry really is showing what the server 
says it has, but apparently duplicate suppression is a useful feature.

Maybe the right choice of name would pull the Other Users and Shared Folders to the top or bottom of 
the folder list, so they&apos;re not amongst real personal folders.  Will check.

We might check standard namespace too.  Not being in production yet, we can change our minds.
</thetext>
          </long_desc>
      
      

    </bug>

</bugzilla>