<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes" ?>
<!DOCTYPE bugzilla SYSTEM "https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/bugzilla.dtd">

<bugzilla version="3.2.5.1-2"
          urlbase="https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/"
          maintainer="Dave McMurtrie &lt;dave64@andrew.cmu.edu&gt;"
>

    <bug>
          <bug_id>2898</bug_id>
          
          <creation_ts>2006-12-13 18:32 EDT</creation_ts>
          <short_desc>sieve_allowreferrals option patch breaks murder setups</short_desc>
          <delta_ts>2006-12-19 13:18:39 EDT</delta_ts>
          <reporter_accessible>1</reporter_accessible>
          <cclist_accessible>1</cclist_accessible>
          <classification_id>1</classification_id>
          <classification>Unclassified</classification>
          <product>Cyrus IMAP</product>
          <component>Murder</component>
          <version>2.2.x</version>
          <rep_platform>Other</rep_platform>
          <op_sys>Linux</op_sys>
          <bug_status>NEW</bug_status>
          
          
          <bug_file_loc>http://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/bugreport.cgi?bug=400747</bug_file_loc>
          
          
          <priority>P2</priority>
          <bug_severity>bug</bug_severity>
          <target_milestone>Future</target_milestone>
          
          
          
          <everconfirmed>1</everconfirmed>
          <reporter name="Sven Mueller">cyrus@incase.de</reporter>
          <assigned_to name="Ken Murchison">murch@andrew.cmu.edu</assigned_to>
          <cc>400747-submitter@bugs.debian.org</cc>
    
    <cc>400747@bugs.debian.org</cc>
          <qa_contact name="The Cyrus Bugzilla List">cyrus-bugzilla@lists.andrew.cmu.edu</qa_contact>

      

      

      
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Sven Mueller">cyrus@incase.de</who>
            <bug_when>2006-12-13 18:32:46 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Hi,

As reported in a mail on the cyrus-devel mailinglist (with a
non-sense/incomplete subject &quot;Change to allow&quot; - sounds like a spam subject), we
received a bug report which we were able to track down to our application of the
sieve_allowreferrals CVS changeset to the 2.2.13 tarball. It seems that it
breaks murder setups, at least with the default setting of issueing referrals.
The package maintainers all don&apos;t have a murder setup to check this more
thoroughly, but this changeset is either defective or it should have a different
default setting (not to break existing setups) - if that would work - or it
needs additional documentation to tell admins how to make sure that this feature
works correctly.

Regards,
Sven</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Ken Murchison">murch@andrew.cmu.edu</who>
            <bug_when>2006-12-13 20:22:55 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>*** Bug 2899 has been marked as a duplicate of this bug. ***</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Ken Murchison">murch@andrew.cmu.edu</who>
            <bug_when>2006-12-13 20:26:26 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>2.2.x frontends have always issued referrals for Sieve which have been used
extensively in the production Murder at CMU.  We implemented the option so that
Sieve referrals could be disabled, thus proxying the traffic.  I&apos;ll double check
the patch, but in its default configuration, the code path should be the same as
it always has been.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Sven Mueller">cyrus@incase.de</who>
            <bug_when>2006-12-13 20:49:43 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Hi Ken. 

Thanks for the quick response. I just had an idea: Ken, could you have a look at
the original bug report and tell me wether a rebuilt cyrus-sasl lib (same ABI
version but possibly some options changed or error correction patches applied)
without a rebuild of cyrus-imapd could have caused those errors?. Since I think
that there was an update to the Debian cyrus-sasl packages after our cyrus-imapd
upload. And to track the bug down, we asked the reporter to rebuild the package
without the patch in question applied. I&apos;m just wondering wether the rebuild and
not the removed patch could be the cure to the problem.

Regards,
Sven</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Ken Murchison">murch@andrew.cmu.edu</who>
            <bug_when>2006-12-14 18:39:25 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Its possible that the changes that I had to make to saslclient.c, which has
authentication code used by all proxies, broke something in the mupdate client.
 Can you get a protocol dump of one of the proxies trying to authenticate to the
mupdate server?</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Ken Murchison">murch@andrew.cmu.edu</who>
            <bug_when>2006-12-19 09:06:14 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>I just tested the latest 2.2 code from CVS and the latest SASL code from CVS and
I can&apos;t reproduce this problem.  All of my services properly authenticate to
mupdate master using PLAIN.
</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Sven Mueller">cyrus@incase.de</who>
            <bug_when>2006-12-19 10:22:58 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Jochen:

Since you have a setup where this error occured: Could you please try to fetch
the most recent _sources_ of the cyrus-imapd package, re-enable the 0019* patch,
build the package and check wether it works. With Kens inability to reproduce
the problem, it seems to me that this problem was in fact caused by updating
libsasl2 after cyrus-imapd had been built, so a rebuild against the most recent
libsasl2 with the patch enabled should work again.
We would really be grateful if you could help us here. The upstream patch would
be a nice thing to include in future package versions.

Ken: Thanks for trying to reproduce the problem. Unfortunately noone from the
Debian packaging team has a murder setup at hand to debug this, so we really
appreciate any help from you (and Jochen, see above) in finding the root of the
problem.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Ken Murchison">murch@andrew.cmu.edu</who>
            <bug_when>2006-12-19 10:25:58 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Is it possible that your patch 0019, only includes selected Cyrus patches, and
not a complete set (ones with the same commit message)?</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Sven Mueller">cyrus@incase.de</who>
            <bug_when>2006-12-19 13:07:06 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>&lt;rant&gt;This is one of the occasions where I wished you were using a more decent
VCS (like subversion for example) with atomic commits or provided some dump of
your repository from time to time (so that one could convert that to a local
subversion repository).&lt;/rant&gt; ;-)

Anyway, I checked as much as I could and didn&apos;t find anything in that set which
isn&apos;t in our file (which you could find at
https://mail.incase.de/svn/cyrus22/trunk/cyrus-imapd-2.2.13/debian/patches/0019-upstream-sieve_allowreferrals.dpatch
if you want to cross-check).

</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Ken Murchison">murch@andrew.cmu.edu</who>
            <bug_when>2006-12-19 13:18:39 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Your patch looks complete to me.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
      
      

    </bug>

</bugzilla>