<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes" ?>
<!DOCTYPE bugzilla SYSTEM "https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/bugzilla.dtd">

<bugzilla version="3.2.5.1-2"
          urlbase="https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/"
          maintainer="Dave McMurtrie &lt;dave64@andrew.cmu.edu&gt;"
>

    <bug>
          <bug_id>2985</bug_id>
          
          <creation_ts>2007-08-27 15:18 EDT</creation_ts>
          <short_desc>People forget to cancel their vacation message</short_desc>
          <delta_ts>2013-06-13 16:13:39 EDT</delta_ts>
          <reporter_accessible>1</reporter_accessible>
          <cclist_accessible>1</cclist_accessible>
          <classification_id>1</classification_id>
          <classification>Unclassified</classification>
          <product>Cyrus IMAP</product>
          <component>Sieve</component>
          <version>2.3.x</version>
          <rep_platform>All</rep_platform>
          <op_sys>All</op_sys>
          <bug_status>NEW</bug_status>
          
          
          
          
          
          <priority>P3</priority>
          <bug_severity>enhancement</bug_severity>
          <target_milestone>Future</target_milestone>
          
          
          
          <everconfirmed>1</everconfirmed>
          <reporter name="Gary Mills">mills@cc.umanitoba.ca</reporter>
          <assigned_to name="Ken Murchison">murch@andrew.cmu.edu</assigned_to>
          <cc>awilliam@whitemice.org</cc>
    
    <cc>rudy.gevaert@ugent.be</cc>
          

      

      

      
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Gary Mills">mills@cc.umanitoba.ca</who>
            <bug_when>2007-08-27 15:18:36 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>One of the complaints I get regularly about the vacation feature of sieve is
that there&apos;s no way to set an expiry date at the same time that you set up the
vacation message.  When people return from vacation, they often forget to cancel
their vacation message.  There&apos;s nothing visible in their e-mail reader to remind
them that the auto-response is still being sent out.  Setting an expiry date at
the same time as you create the vacation message would be one solution.  I&apos;m sure
there are others.  In any case, this is a feature request.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Ken Murchison">murch@andrew.cmu.edu</who>
            <bug_when>2007-10-18 07:51:51 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>In the interest of portability, I don&apos;t want to extend the syntax of the vacation action without corresponding changes in the specification.  Unfortunately, the vacation spec is already sitting in the RFC editor queue, so such changes will have to wait for the next revision.  Would it help if we add an option to have the autoresponse Bcc&apos;d to the original recipient?</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Gary Mills">mills@cc.umanitoba.ca</who>
            <bug_when>2007-10-19 12:11:54 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>I don&apos;t think that BCC would help in this case; sure, it would give them
a reminder, but people would find this even more confusing.  Some would
complain that they now get two copies of each message.  As this problem
is not urgent, I&apos;d prefer to wait for the specification to get updated.
</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Adam Tauno Williams">awilliam@whitemice.org</who>
            <bug_when>2010-08-03 06:07:36 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Horde&apos;s Ingo provides an interesting solution to this issue - it can create a rule which matches a date range using regular expressions.  This seems to work very well, at least on a current version of Cyrus/SIEVE with the required extensions.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Rudy Gevaert">rudy.gevaert@ugent.be</who>
            <bug_when>2013-06-13 16:13:39 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>(In reply to comment #3)
&gt; Horde&apos;s Ingo provides an interesting solution to this issue - it can create a
&gt; rule which matches a date range using regular expressions.  This seems to work
&gt; very well, at least on a current version of Cyrus/SIEVE with the required
&gt; extensions.

Yes it works very will.  I think this bug should be closed as a work around exists.  Implementing  Bug 3724 would also help tough.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
      
      

    </bug>

</bugzilla>