<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes" ?>
<!DOCTYPE bugzilla SYSTEM "https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/bugzilla.dtd">

<bugzilla version="3.2.5.1-2"
          urlbase="https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/"
          maintainer="Dave McMurtrie &lt;dave64@andrew.cmu.edu&gt;"
>

    <bug>
          <bug_id>3019</bug_id>
          
          <creation_ts>2008-01-04 01:17 EDT</creation_ts>
          <short_desc>Quick answers for some questions</short_desc>
          <delta_ts>2010-10-25 18:46:44 EDT</delta_ts>
          <reporter_accessible>1</reporter_accessible>
          <cclist_accessible>1</cclist_accessible>
          <classification_id>1</classification_id>
          <classification>Unclassified</classification>
          <product>Cyrus IMAP</product>
          <component>documentation</component>
          <version>2.3.x</version>
          <rep_platform>All</rep_platform>
          <op_sys>All</op_sys>
          <bug_status>CLOSED</bug_status>
          <resolution>FIXED</resolution>
          
          <bug_file_loc>http://cyrusimap.web.cmu.edu/imapd/questions.html</bug_file_loc>
          
          
          <priority>P5</priority>
          <bug_severity>bug</bug_severity>
          <target_milestone>Future</target_milestone>
          
          
          
          <everconfirmed>1</everconfirmed>
          <reporter name="Chris Pepper">pepper@reppep.com</reporter>
          <assigned_to name="Ken Murchison">murch@andrew.cmu.edu</assigned_to>
          
          

      

      

      
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Chris Pepper">pepper@reppep.com</who>
            <bug_when>2008-01-04 01:17:48 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>•	Why is it so hard to get imapd working with Red Hat&apos;s shadow password implementation?

	Normally, /etc/shadow is only readable by root, but Cyrus IMAPd does not normally run as root.

	•	When does imapd advertise PLAIN? When does it accept plaintext logins?

	Unless otherwise configured, recent versions of Cyrus IMAPd only advertise PLAIN on encrypted connections IMAP/SSL or POP/SSL ports, or after STARTTLS). See also, all occurrences of &apos;plaintext&apos; in &lt;http://cyrusimap.web.cmu.edu/imapd/man/imapd.conf.5.html&gt;.

	•	What are the advantages of LMTP?
	•	How do I configure Sendmail to use LMTP?
	•	How do I configure Postfix to work with Cyrus? To use LMTP?
	•	How can I run LMTP over TCP? Why would I want to?

	If for scaling reasons it&apos;s impractical to run SMTP (and spam/virus scanning) on the same server as mailbox access, you can use LMTP to bridge messages from the SMTP server(s) - typically running Sendmail or Postfix - to the mail store servers (Cyrus).

	•	What are the performance implications of single-instance store (as of 1.6.22)?
	•	How should I configure partitions to deal with a large number of users?

	The key is not to over-subscribe any partitions. Avoid putting too many users on any one partition, such that read/write performance becomes unacceptable. Good RAID performance (plenty of read/write cache, and perhaps RAID 10 instead of RAID 5) will improve the number of users a partition can serve. To benefit from multiple partitions, each should be on its own set of disks, served by an unsaturated interface (FC, SCSI, SAS, SATA, etc) to the host running Cyrus. 

See &lt;http://cyrusimap.web.cmu.edu/imapd/install-perf.html&gt; for general performance guidelines. See metapartition_files &amp;amp; metapartition-name in &lt;http://cyrusimap.web.cmu.edu/imapd/man/imapd.conf.5.html&gt; for additional Cyrus which can help with performance, especially if you have access to high-speed storage (faster than disks).</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Ken Murchison">murch@andrew.cmu.edu</who>
            <bug_when>2008-01-09 17:05:19 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Moved stuff from questions.html to faq.html using a lot of your text</thetext>
          </long_desc>
      
      

    </bug>

</bugzilla>