<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes" ?>
<!DOCTYPE bugzilla SYSTEM "https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/bugzilla.dtd">

<bugzilla version="3.2.5.1-2"
          urlbase="https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/"
          maintainer="Dave McMurtrie &lt;dave64@andrew.cmu.edu&gt;"
>

    <bug>
          <bug_id>3049</bug_id>
          
          <creation_ts>2008-03-29 10:05 EDT</creation_ts>
          <short_desc>Sieve forwarding loop destroys e-mail</short_desc>
          <delta_ts>2013-09-18 17:15:34 EDT</delta_ts>
          <reporter_accessible>1</reporter_accessible>
          <cclist_accessible>1</cclist_accessible>
          <classification_id>1</classification_id>
          <classification>Unclassified</classification>
          <product>Cyrus IMAP</product>
          <component>Sieve</component>
          <version>2.3.x</version>
          <rep_platform>Sun</rep_platform>
          <op_sys>Solaris</op_sys>
          <bug_status>ASSIGNED</bug_status>
          
          
          
          
          
          <priority>P3</priority>
          <bug_severity>bug</bug_severity>
          <target_milestone>2.5-next</target_milestone>
          
          
          
          <everconfirmed>1</everconfirmed>
          <reporter name="Gary Mills">mills@cc.umanitoba.ca</reporter>
          <assigned_to name="Ken Murchison">murch@andrew.cmu.edu</assigned_to>
          <cc>ana.ribas@upcnet.es</cc>
    
    <cc>brong@fastmail.fm</cc>
    
    <cc>fedoraproject@cyberpear.com</cc>
          

      

      

      
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Gary Mills">mills@cc.umanitoba.ca</who>
            <bug_when>2008-03-29 10:05:58 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Once again, we had somebody use the sieve facility to redirect e-mail
back to the same mailbox and then go on vacation.  This sets up a
forwarding loop which cyrus breaks by discarding the e-mail.  During
this vacation, all of the person&apos;s e-mail disappeared.

Shouldn&apos;t we have a better solution to this problem?  Some people
expect that forwarding e-mail to yourself should work; nobody expects
the messages to vanish without a trace.

Once the message has been `seen&apos; and is about to be forwarded again,
it would be better to deliver the message into the mailbox, rather
than deleting it.  Is this possible with the current design of the
duplicate delivery database?</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Ken Murchison">murch@andrew.cmu.edu</who>
            <bug_when>2008-09-24 07:21:06 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>If we made the second attempt to forward a message a failure rather than a silent success, then the sieve engine would implicitly keep the message.

We&apos;d have to look at any unintended consequences if we make this change.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Bron Gondwana">brong@fastmail.fm</who>
            <bug_when>2011-07-03 17:26:15 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>*** Bug 3418 has been marked as a duplicate of this bug. ***</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Bron Gondwana">brong@fastmail.fm</who>
            <bug_when>2011-07-03 17:30:20 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Hi Ken - you commented on this one.

How were you intending to detect the loop?  Is sieve adding a header that we can detect as being the same instance, so that if the same message comes back a second time then we know it&apos;s the same?

I guess the other approach is to use the duplicate db to detect that the message has already been forwarded/rejected/vacationed.

I guess the worst case for always dumping it into the INBOX and suppressing any further message generation would be duplicate copies, the first one filed into a different directory, and the second one filed into INBOX.  Not a disaster usually.

We also had a lot of discussion about using the Date: header as part of the duplicate detection magic.  From what I can, this is pretty trivial since we generate a hash anyway, and can just add the Date field to the hash.

I&apos;m happy to take the ticket and do the code, I just want to double check what your plans were!

Thanks,

Bron.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Bron Gondwana">brong@fastmail.fm</who>
            <bug_when>2011-07-03 17:31:17 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>targetting for 2.5-next, we may not backport to 2.4 depending how invasive it looks.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
      
      

    </bug>

</bugzilla>