<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes" ?>
<!DOCTYPE bugzilla SYSTEM "https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/bugzilla.dtd">

<bugzilla version="3.2.5.1-2"
          urlbase="https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/"
          maintainer="Dave McMurtrie &lt;dave64@andrew.cmu.edu&gt;"
>

    <bug>
          <bug_id>3101</bug_id>
          
          <creation_ts>2008-10-13 15:15 EDT</creation_ts>
          <short_desc>Murder inadequately documented</short_desc>
          <delta_ts>2010-10-14 05:34:56 EDT</delta_ts>
          <reporter_accessible>1</reporter_accessible>
          <cclist_accessible>1</cclist_accessible>
          <classification_id>1</classification_id>
          <classification>Unclassified</classification>
          <product>Cyrus IMAP</product>
          <component>documentation</component>
          <version>2.3.x</version>
          <rep_platform>All</rep_platform>
          <op_sys>All</op_sys>
          <bug_status>NEW</bug_status>
          
          
          
          
          
          <priority>P5</priority>
          <bug_severity>bug</bug_severity>
          <target_milestone>Future</target_milestone>
          
          
          
          <everconfirmed>1</everconfirmed>
          <reporter name="Nic Bernstein">nic@onlight.com</reporter>
          <assigned_to name="Ken Murchison">murch@andrew.cmu.edu</assigned_to>
          <cc>wes@umich.edu</cc>
          

      

      

      
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Nic Bernstein">nic@onlight.com</who>
            <bug_when>2008-10-13 15:15:43 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>There is a lack of clear documentation on the proper configuration and deployment of Cyrus IMAP murder.  This is a general deficiency, not limited to the man pages, web site, documentation text and html pages or wiki.  The following bullet points refer to specific issues.

* Better explanations are needed of the interaction of hostname_password, hostname_mechs, force_client_sasl_mech, sasl_mech_list and allowplaintext.

* The requirement for TLS when using PLAIN (such as in an LDAP environment) should be clearly stated.  Also, it must be clear that in order to enforce TLS allowplaintext must be false (some packagers change this default) and that this does not interfere with &quot;sasl_mech_list: PLAIN&quot;

* The meaning of &quot;short hostname&quot; should be made clear, and the behavior of ignoring everything to the right of the first dot (period, full-stop, &quot;.&quot;) in configuration settings calling for &quot;short hostnames&quot; should likewise be made clear (and the ramifications of this).

There is a general lack of clarity regarding the interaction of various SASL related settings in a murder: which settings properly belong on backends, frontends or mupdate masters; how does the proxy process effect the selection of mechanisms; how can one test for the correct operation of these.

Lastly, examples, examples, examples.  There just aren&apos;t enough examples of typical configurations: unified murder; standard with multiple backends, multiple frontends; etc.  Most people come to understand configuration via examples, yet the current documentation comes up short in this regard.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Wes Craig">wes@umich.edu</who>
            <bug_when>2008-10-31 11:12:21 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>I think this is really several reports, and we should break it up.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
      
      

    </bug>

</bugzilla>