<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes" ?>
<!DOCTYPE bugzilla SYSTEM "https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/bugzilla.dtd">

<bugzilla version="3.2.5.1-2"
          urlbase="https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/"
          maintainer="Dave McMurtrie &lt;dave64@andrew.cmu.edu&gt;"
>

    <bug>
          <bug_id>3199</bug_id>
          
          <creation_ts>2010-03-12 06:11 EDT</creation_ts>
          <short_desc>Messages deleted via POP3 remain in spool</short_desc>
          <delta_ts>2010-03-12 15:22:38 EDT</delta_ts>
          <reporter_accessible>1</reporter_accessible>
          <cclist_accessible>1</cclist_accessible>
          <classification_id>1</classification_id>
          <classification>Unclassified</classification>
          <product>Cyrus IMAP</product>
          <component>POP</component>
          <version>2.3.x</version>
          <rep_platform>PC</rep_platform>
          <op_sys>Linux</op_sys>
          <bug_status>NEW</bug_status>
          
          
          
          
          
          <priority>P5</priority>
          <bug_severity>bug</bug_severity>
          <target_milestone>Future</target_milestone>
          
          
          
          <everconfirmed>1</everconfirmed>
          <reporter name="Bogdan Stancescu">bogdan@moongate.ro</reporter>
          <assigned_to name="Ken Murchison">murch@andrew.cmu.edu</assigned_to>
          
          

      

      

      
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Bogdan Stancescu">bogdan@moongate.ro</who>
            <bug_when>2010-03-12 06:11:52 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>The summary says it all. CentOS 5.4 final, x64, sendmail + cyrus-imapd 2.3.16.

I verified explicitly that clients issue a DELE command with Wireshark -- they do, and Cyrus acknowledges, but all mail stays in /var/spool/imap until the mailboxes are rebuilt. I ended up with a weekly cron job.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Ken Murchison">murch@andrew.cmu.edu</who>
            <bug_when>2010-03-12 06:20:27 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Do you have &apos;delete_mode: delayed&apos; configured in imapd.conf?</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Bogdan Stancescu">bogdan@moongate.ro</who>
            <bug_when>2010-03-12 06:26:21 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>There is no explicit setting for delete_mode in imapd.conf, so I&apos;m using whatever&apos;s the default. I could try setting it explicitly for immediate removal and test that way, but I don&apos;t know the setting.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Ken Murchison">murch@andrew.cmu.edu</who>
            <bug_when>2010-03-12 06:35:53 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Once again, I can&apos;t reproduce your problem.  Are you compiling Cyrus yourself, or using a prepackaged version?  How do you know that the code hasn&apos;t been modified?

How do you know that your POP client is properly sending the DELE and QUIT commands?  If the client disconnects without sending QUIT, the message WILL NOT be deleted as required by the POP3 spec.

The pop3d code has been stable for quite a while and nobody else has reported this problem.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Bogdan Stancescu">bogdan@moongate.ro</who>
            <bug_when>2010-03-12 15:22:38 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>I could check and share the entire dialog between the server and the client, that&apos;s not an issue.

But you raise an interesting point regarding the package; unfortunately I can&apos;t remember how I upgraded Cyrus, whether from source or using an RPM (long story, fact is I was in a rush and I compiled some stuff, installed some RPMs and so on). I could provide you with checksums of whatever binaries you deem relevant, if you think that&apos;s a viable option.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
      
      

    </bug>

</bugzilla>