<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes" ?>
<!DOCTYPE bugzilla SYSTEM "https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/bugzilla.dtd">

<bugzilla version="3.2.5.1-2"
          urlbase="https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/"
          maintainer="Dave McMurtrie &lt;dave64@andrew.cmu.edu&gt;"
>

    <bug>
          <bug_id>3213</bug_id>
          
          <creation_ts>2010-05-04 15:14 EDT</creation_ts>
          <short_desc>Connecting to a newer backend renders proxyd thread unusable for older backends</short_desc>
          <delta_ts>2010-05-28 15:34:28 EDT</delta_ts>
          <reporter_accessible>1</reporter_accessible>
          <cclist_accessible>1</cclist_accessible>
          <classification_id>1</classification_id>
          <classification>Unclassified</classification>
          <product>Cyrus IMAP</product>
          <component>Murder</component>
          <version>2.3.x</version>
          <rep_platform>PC</rep_platform>
          <op_sys>Linux</op_sys>
          <bug_status>NEW</bug_status>
          
          
          
          
          
          <priority>P5</priority>
          <bug_severity>blocker</bug_severity>
          <target_milestone>Future</target_milestone>
          
          
          
          <everconfirmed>1</everconfirmed>
          <reporter name="Torsten Schlabach">tschlabach@gmx.net</reporter>
          <assigned_to name="Ken Murchison">murch@andrew.cmu.edu</assigned_to>
          <cc>wes@umich.edu</cc>
          

      

      

      
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Torsten Schlabach">tschlabach@gmx.net</who>
            <bug_when>2010-05-04 15:14:59 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>If you run a proxyd as part of a Cyrus Murder, either 2.2 or 2.3, and you have some backends which are 2.1 and others which are 2.2, the following problem is observed.

Sometimes, but not always, any IMAP command will result in the error message:

Server(s) unavailable to complete operation

on the client. At the same time, in the logs you will find:

couldn&apos;t authenticate to backend server: bad protocol / cancel

If you retry after a short period of time, the problem goes away and the connect works.

Note:

Some other people have seen a similar problem at 
http://irbs.net/internet/info-cyrus/0808/0067.html

We were able to trace this down and make it reproduceable as follows:

If the same proxyd thread which has been used to connect to a 2.2 backend gets reused to connect to a 2.1 backend, the problem comes up. The reason why it fixes itself after a short period of time is that the proxyd thread will terminate and a new proxyd thread will be started, which then has a fresh initialization and thus no problem.

Any hints into code investigation could be useful.

The thread linked about talkes about an &quot;errant bind() call in backend_connect&quot; which was removed in 2.3. As we still have this problem in 2.3.8, I assume, this wasn&apos;t the problem.

Please ask if we failed to explain the scenario properly.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
      
      

    </bug>

</bugzilla>