<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes" ?>
<!DOCTYPE bugzilla SYSTEM "https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/bugzilla.dtd">

<bugzilla version="3.2.5.1-2"
          urlbase="https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/"
          maintainer="Dave McMurtrie &lt;dave64@andrew.cmu.edu&gt;"
>

    <bug>
          <bug_id>3216</bug_id>
          
          <creation_ts>2010-05-07 08:07 EDT</creation_ts>
          <short_desc>Mail filesystem time keeping upon copying/moving</short_desc>
          <delta_ts>2010-05-07 08:07:07 EDT</delta_ts>
          <reporter_accessible>1</reporter_accessible>
          <cclist_accessible>1</cclist_accessible>
          <classification_id>1</classification_id>
          <classification>Unclassified</classification>
          <product>Cyrus IMAP</product>
          <component>IMAP</component>
          <version>2.3.x</version>
          <rep_platform>All</rep_platform>
          <op_sys>Linux</op_sys>
          <bug_status>NEW</bug_status>
          
          
          
          
          
          <priority>P5</priority>
          <bug_severity>enhancement</bug_severity>
          <target_milestone>Future</target_milestone>
          
          
          
          <everconfirmed>1</everconfirmed>
          <reporter name="Julien Coloos">julien.coloos@atos.net</reporter>
          <assigned_to name="Ken Murchison">murch@andrew.cmu.edu</assigned_to>
          
          

      

      

      
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Julien Coloos">julien.coloos@atos.net</who>
            <bug_when>2010-05-07 08:07:07 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Context: upon reconstructing a mailbox, if index data are missing, cyrus guesses the INTERNALDATE thanks to each message file write time.
In recent versions, the UNDUMP feature has been altered to restore the message file write and access time according to the INTERNALDATE, thus allowing to keep valuable data if a reconstruct would be needed after moving a mailbox through DUMP/UNDUMP.

However, when copying a message file (for example with the IMAP COPY command), or moving it to another partition (with the IMAP RENAME command), the original message file time is not applied on the copied data (while INTERNALDATE is kept).
In case of reconstruct, the copied message could thus lose the original value of its INTERNALDATE (replaced by the time at which the mail was copied).


To prevent this, and since I believe most of copied files happen to be messages, the mailbox_copyfile function (imap/mailbox.c) could be modified to also copy file access/write time upon success (unless hardlinking was used of course).
Do you think this would be as useful as what is currently done upon UNDUMP ?</thetext>
          </long_desc>
      
      

    </bug>

</bugzilla>