<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes" ?>
<!DOCTYPE bugzilla SYSTEM "https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/bugzilla.dtd">

<bugzilla version="3.2.5.1-2"
          urlbase="https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/"
          maintainer="Dave McMurtrie &lt;dave64@andrew.cmu.edu&gt;"
>

    <bug>
          <bug_id>3294</bug_id>
          
          <creation_ts>2010-10-28 08:16 EDT</creation_ts>
          <short_desc>Corruption of cyrus.index renders LMTP socket unusable for delivery</short_desc>
          <delta_ts>2010-11-08 10:33:07 EDT</delta_ts>
          <reporter_accessible>1</reporter_accessible>
          <cclist_accessible>1</cclist_accessible>
          <classification_id>1</classification_id>
          <classification>Unclassified</classification>
          <product>Cyrus IMAP</product>
          <component>IMAP</component>
          <version>2.4.0</version>
          <rep_platform>Sun</rep_platform>
          <op_sys>Solaris</op_sys>
          <bug_status>CLOSED</bug_status>
          <resolution>FIXED</resolution>
          
          
          
          
          <priority>P1</priority>
          <bug_severity>blocker</bug_severity>
          <target_milestone>2.4.3</target_milestone>
          
          
          
          <everconfirmed>1</everconfirmed>
          <reporter name="Leena Heino">Leena.Heino@uta.fi</reporter>
          <assigned_to name="Bron Gondwana">brong@fastmail.fm</assigned_to>
          <cc>brong@fastmail.fm</cc>
    
    <cc>vanmeeuwen@kolabsys.com</cc>
          <qa_contact name="The Cyrus Bugzilla List">cyrus-bugzilla@lists.andrew.cmu.edu</qa_contact>

      

      

      
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Leena Heino">Leena.Heino@uta.fi</who>
            <bug_when>2010-10-28 08:16:31 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>We have had now a couple of cases where reconstruct fails to open cyrus.index. Only error is: Arithmetic Exception

Tracing the program it seems to die when it tries to mmap cyrus.index:
open(&quot;/var/mail/imap/f/user/foo/cyrus.index&quot;, O_RDWR) = 7
fstat(7, 0xFFBF9F68)                            = 0
mmap(0x00000000, 442368, PROT_READ, MAP_SHARED, 7, 0) = 0xFE390000
    Incurred fault #8, FLTIZDIV  %pc = 0xFECA4628
      siginfo: SIGFPE FPE_INTDIV addr=0xFECA4628
    Received signal #8, SIGFPE [default]
      siginfo: SIGFPE FPE_INTDIV addr=0xFECA4628

When lmtpd encounters broken cyrus.index file it exits immediately. This has a nasty side effect that it blocks mail deliveries to this user and group of other unrelated users.

What happens is this:
1. Sendmail begins queue run
2. Sendmail tries to deliver message with lmtp to a user that has broken index file, lmtpd exits
3. Message is requeued to later delivery with status: &quot;Deferred: Connection reset by localhost&quot;
4. Sendmail tries to deliver another message from queue using cached socket connection. Lmtpd process listening to the socket has exited at step 2. This message also gets status: &quot;Deferred: Connection reset by localhost&quot;
5. go to step 4 and repeat until queue has been processed
6. Messages begin to build up at mail queue.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Jeroen van Meeuwen (Kolab Systems)">vanmeeuwen@kolabsys.com</who>
            <bug_when>2010-10-28 08:32:33 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Is 2.4.2 the version of Cyrus IMAP you are indeed experiencing this with?

How regularly does the cyrus.index corruption occur, and can you think of any reason why or how it could corrupt?

Also, I suppose it&apos;d be useful to know whether Cyrus IMAP is still running when you issue the reconstruct.

Thanks!</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Leena Heino">Leena.Heino@uta.fi</who>
            <bug_when>2010-10-28 08:57:16 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Current version is: v2.4.0 2010/08/04 18:57:36

This random index corruption has now happened at least twice. Though there could be more broken index files.

What makes this whole case so problematic is that a couple of broken index files can render the system unable to deliver messages to other unrelated users. Lmtpd should issue an error, not exit when it encounters a broken index file it cannot handle.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Jeroen van Meeuwen (Kolab Systems)">vanmeeuwen@kolabsys.com</who>
            <bug_when>2010-10-28 09:35:52 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>(In reply to comment #2)
&gt; Current version is: v2.4.0 2010/08/04 18:57:36
&gt; 

So reflected in the issue report now.

&gt; This random index corruption has now happened at least twice. Though there
&gt; could be more broken index files.
&gt; 
&gt; What makes this whole case so problematic is that a couple of broken index
&gt; files can render the system unable to deliver messages to other unrelated
&gt; users. Lmtpd should issue an error, not exit when it encounters a broken index
&gt; file it cannot handle.

Fair enough. Let me reflect such in the title of the bug as well, and bump the priority/severity.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Jeroen van Meeuwen (Kolab Systems)">vanmeeuwen@kolabsys.com</who>
            <bug_when>2010-10-28 09:40:47 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>*** Bug 3289 has been marked as a duplicate of this bug. ***</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Bron Gondwana">brong@fastmail.fm</who>
            <bug_when>2010-11-05 08:46:46 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Need to make sure we&apos;re on top of this one for 2.4.3, this is serious - corrupted mailboxes suck - but we need to handle them as nicely as possible.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Bron Gondwana">brong@fastmail.fm</who>
            <bug_when>2010-11-07 23:35:26 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Hang on - I just re-read this in more detail, and I don&apos;t think it&apos;s Cyrus&apos; fault.

WTF Sendmail.

2. Sendmail tries to deliver message with lmtp to a user that has broken index
file, lmtpd exits
3. Message is requeued to later delivery with status: &quot;Deferred: Connection
reset by localhost&quot;
4. Sendmail tries to deliver another message from queue using cached socket
connection.

Hello Sendmail.  It&apos;s closed.  Why on earth are you trying to use a cached connection that&apos;s closed???  Totally bogus.

Can you configure Sendmail to open a new connection each time?  Or get yourself a real MTA?

I think lmtpd might even be saying &quot;goodbye&quot; first.  There&apos;s no guarantee that the lmtpd will sit around forever waiting to chat to you.  It&apos;s perfectly within its rights to close the connection.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Leena Heino">Leena.Heino@uta.fi</who>
            <bug_when>2010-11-08 01:06:19 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>When the lmtpd encounters bad cyrus.index and/or cyrus.cache does it give some sort of error to lmtp side? No it does not and that is the problem. The lmtpd process just exits. If it did give some sort of indication of a problem and where this problem might to the connecting side then the sendmail/postfix would be able log it in their logs.

Can sendmail be made to deliver only one message per lmtp connection, yes of course.

But what happens when one message has more than one recipient and one of the recipients has broken cyrus.index and/or broken cyrus.cache? The lmtpd just exits, no errors messages are returned to the connecting side.

Can sendmail be made to deliver one message to one recipient per lmtp connection even when the message has multiple recipients, yes of course. But this breaks single instance store.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Bron Gondwana">brong@fastmail.fm</who>
            <bug_when>2010-11-08 01:24:34 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Here&apos;s how Cyrus handles a corrupt mailbox (me hand-corrupting a mailbox)

$ telnet slot2 2003
Trying 127.0.0.52...
Connected to slot2.
Escape character is &apos;^]&apos;.
220 test_slot2_3351 Cyrus LMTP git2.4.2+33 server ready
LHLO me
250-test_slot2_3351
250-8BITMIME
250-ENHANCEDSTATUSCODES
250-PIPELINING
250-SIZE
250-AUTH EXTERNAL
250 IGNOREQUOTA
MAIL FROM:&lt;brong@fastmail.fm&gt;
250 2.1.0 ok
RCPT TO:&lt;foo&gt;
451 4.2.0 Mailbox has an invalid format
RCPT TO:&lt;bar&gt;
250 2.1.5 ok
DATA
354 go ahead
Subject: testing

stuff
.
250 2.1.5 Ok SESSIONID=&lt;test_slot2_3351-3446-1289197088-1&gt;


Perfectly well - rejected the message to &lt;foo&gt;, but accepted to &lt;bar&gt;.

So the issue is what happens when your imapd CRASHES.  Now it shouldn&apos;t have crashed trying to mmap the file, but that&apos;s a separate issue from the behaviour of lmtpd, which is fine.

So - crash handling - once it segfaults it&apos;s game over!  That&apos;s a real bug for sure, but the behaviour of lmtpd itself isn&apos;t.

---------------------------

So the question is - why did it segfault?  Do you still have this broken mailbox around?  Can you create another one reliably?  I would want to see what &apos;stat&apos; is returning about the file.  The &quot;442368&quot; value there will be the file size plus some slack - map_shared always mmaps up to a page boundary.

It looks like the calculation error is actually immediately after that mmap though.  I&apos;ll look into that code and write another message about it...</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Bron Gondwana">brong@fastmail.fm</who>
            <bug_when>2010-11-08 01:45:54 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Ok - bug found.  It was in upgrade_index.  Thanks for the example file you sent too.  The cause was the first 80 bytes of the file being zero - which caused a bug with a division (isn&apos;t it always the divisions) in upgrade_index.

This will be fixed by tomorrow and in 2.4.3!</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Bron Gondwana">brong@fastmail.fm</who>
            <bug_when>2010-11-08 03:13:47 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Fixed in git - will be in 2.4.3</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Jeroen van Meeuwen (Kolab Systems)">vanmeeuwen@kolabsys.com</who>
            <bug_when>2010-11-08 10:33:07 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Nice catch here, Bron, and thanks Leena for follow-up!</thetext>
          </long_desc>
      
      

    </bug>

</bugzilla>