<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes" ?>
<!DOCTYPE bugzilla SYSTEM "https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/bugzilla.dtd">

<bugzilla version="3.2.5.1-2"
          urlbase="https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/"
          maintainer="Dave McMurtrie &lt;dave64@andrew.cmu.edu&gt;"
>

    <bug>
          <bug_id>3341</bug_id>
          
          <creation_ts>2010-11-18 08:13 EDT</creation_ts>
          <short_desc>Allow _ in hostnames</short_desc>
          <delta_ts>2014-10-21 09:56:08 EDT</delta_ts>
          <reporter_accessible>1</reporter_accessible>
          <cclist_accessible>1</cclist_accessible>
          <classification_id>1</classification_id>
          <classification>Unclassified</classification>
          <product>Cyrus IMAP</product>
          <component>IMAP</component>
          <version>2.4.x (next)</version>
          <rep_platform>PC</rep_platform>
          <op_sys>Linux</op_sys>
          <bug_status>NEW</bug_status>
          
          
          
          
          
          <priority>P3</priority>
          <bug_severity>bug</bug_severity>
          <target_milestone>Future</target_milestone>
          
          
          
          <everconfirmed>1</everconfirmed>
          <reporter name="Bron Gondwana">brong@fastmail.fm</reporter>
          <assigned_to name="Ken Murchison">murch@andrew.cmu.edu</assigned_to>
          <cc>vanmeeuwen@kolabsys.com</cc>
          <qa_contact name="The Cyrus Bugzilla List">cyrus-bugzilla@lists.andrew.cmu.edu</qa_contact>

      

      

      
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Bron Gondwana">brong@fastmail.fm</who>
            <bug_when>2010-11-18 08:13:35 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Strictly, they&apos;re illegal - but most sites don&apos;t complain.

http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hostname#Restrictions_on_valid_host_names says:

A notable example of non-compliance with this specification, Microsoft Windows systems often use underscores in hostnames. Since some systems will reject invalid hostnames while others will not, the use of invalid hostname characters may cause subtle problems in systems that connect to standards-based services. For example, RFC-compliant mail servers will refuse to deliver mail for MS Windows computers with names containing underscores.

...

Liberal in what you accept and all that - I suspect we may be better declaring this little battle lost and just accepting the emails.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Jeroen van Meeuwen (Kolab Systems)">vanmeeuwen@kolabsys.com</who>
            <bug_when>2010-11-18 19:55:38 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Is this an actual problem? If so, where does the problem occur exactly? Can you describe the scenario?</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Bron Gondwana">brong@fastmail.fm</who>
            <bug_when>2010-11-18 21:50:51 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>We have a user receiving emails from a mailing list where the source address has an _ in the hostname part.  Cyrus rejects it, so those emails from the mailing list don&apos;t get through.  Other sites on the mailing list work fine, so it affects this user.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Jeroen van Meeuwen (Kolab Systems)">vanmeeuwen@kolabsys.com</who>
            <bug_when>2010-11-19 04:56:08 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>I would regret to have to run in circles on our end, to fix problems caused by (illegal) mistakes on another end.

That said, I strongly recommend Cyrus remains RFC compliant.

However, if it is an acceptable change of pace, I think a solution can also be to have Cyrus gain the ability to be configured to just blindly accept whatever the MTA passes through, and have all such checking be done &quot;elsewhere&quot; -I&apos;m not sure how feasible that is though, and I&apos;ve not given much thought to any other implications and/or consequences.

The former notwithstanding, if Cyrus were to accept anything not compliant with the RFCs, I suppose this needs to become a setting where the default is in fact RFC compliance, like with 8-bit headers?</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Bron Gondwana">brong@fastmail.fm</who>
            <bug_when>2014-10-21 09:56:08 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Batch moving bugs that won&apos;t be in 2.5</thetext>
          </long_desc>
      
      

    </bug>

</bugzilla>