<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes" ?>
<!DOCTYPE bugzilla SYSTEM "https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/bugzilla.dtd">

<bugzilla version="3.2.5.1-2"
          urlbase="https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/"
          maintainer="Dave McMurtrie &lt;dave64@andrew.cmu.edu&gt;"
>

    <bug>
          <bug_id>3409</bug_id>
          
          <creation_ts>2011-03-01 11:02 EDT</creation_ts>
          <short_desc>configuring serverlist on a backend results in an infinite loop</short_desc>
          <delta_ts>2011-03-16 11:00:33 EDT</delta_ts>
          <reporter_accessible>1</reporter_accessible>
          <cclist_accessible>1</cclist_accessible>
          <classification_id>1</classification_id>
          <classification>Unclassified</classification>
          <product>Cyrus IMAP</product>
          <component>Murder</component>
          <version>2.4.6</version>
          <rep_platform>PC</rep_platform>
          <op_sys>Linux</op_sys>
          <bug_status>NEW</bug_status>
          
          
          
          
          
          <priority>P3</priority>
          <bug_severity>bug</bug_severity>
          <target_milestone>Future</target_milestone>
          
          
          
          <everconfirmed>1</everconfirmed>
          <reporter name="Michael Menge">michael.menge@zdv.uni-tuebingen.de</reporter>
          <assigned_to name="Ken Murchison">murch@andrew.cmu.edu</assigned_to>
          <cc>brong@fastmail.fm</cc>
          <qa_contact name="The Cyrus Bugzilla List">cyrus-bugzilla@lists.andrew.cmu.edu</qa_contact>

      

      

      
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Michael Menge">michael.menge@zdv.uni-tuebingen.de</who>
            <bug_when>2011-03-01 11:02:27 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>if serverlist is configures on a backend
createmailbox without the partition parameter will result 
in trying to find the best backend, connecting to this backend 
and creating the mailbox there. Which might trigger a new round
of finding the best backend.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Bron Gondwana">brong@fastmail.fm</who>
            <bug_when>2011-03-16 06:25:35 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>So don&apos;t do that ;)

Seriously though, I&apos;m assuming the documentation says not to set serverlist on a backend for precisely this reason.

I&apos;m going to leave this bug open (targetted for future) because it would be good to have loop detection - but I&apos;m not sure how you can do it without guaranteeing a servername to DNS mapping, or changing the protocol.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Michael Menge">michael.menge@zdv.uni-tuebingen.de</who>
            <bug_when>2011-03-16 11:00:33 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>
w(Mit Bezug zu comment #1)
&gt; So don&apos;t do that ;)

this was an attempt to avoid Bug 3408
http://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/show_bug.cgi?id=3408

&gt; 
&gt; Seriously though, I&apos;m assuming the documentation says not to set serverlist on
&gt; a backend for precisely this reason.

which documentation do you mean? Man imapd.conf doc/changes.html do only say 
that it is used to finde the best backend, but not that it is unsave to configure it on the backend.

The rest of the documentation and in particular doc/murder-install.html 
do not mention this option at all. 

In an unified config there is only one imapd.conf for backend and frondend, 
so this will result in problems there if we don&apos;t deteckt the loop.

&gt; 
&gt; I&apos;m going to leave this bug open (targetted for future) because it would be
&gt; good to have loop detection - but I&apos;m not sure how you can do it without
&gt; guaranteeing a servername to DNS mapping, or changing the protocol.

If the serverlist is configured and the partition is on given for create mailbox the server asks all backends about the space of all partitions, 
so it does know the best backend and partiton.  

It then connects to the backend and issues create mailbox without the 
partition infromation, which triggers the loop. But it could issue the 
create mailbox with the partition information so the backend does not try 
to find the best backend again.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
      
      

    </bug>

</bugzilla>