<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes" ?>
<!DOCTYPE bugzilla SYSTEM "https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/bugzilla.dtd">

<bugzilla version="3.2.5.1-2"
          urlbase="https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/"
          maintainer="Dave McMurtrie &lt;dave64@andrew.cmu.edu&gt;"
>

    <bug>
          <bug_id>3418</bug_id>
          
          <creation_ts>2011-03-09 07:33 EDT</creation_ts>
          <short_desc>duplicate suppression breaks redirect loops</short_desc>
          <delta_ts>2011-07-03 17:26:15 EDT</delta_ts>
          <reporter_accessible>1</reporter_accessible>
          <cclist_accessible>1</cclist_accessible>
          <classification_id>1</classification_id>
          <classification>Unclassified</classification>
          <product>Cyrus IMAP</product>
          <component>Sieve</component>
          <version>2.3.x</version>
          <rep_platform>All</rep_platform>
          <op_sys>Linux</op_sys>
          <bug_status>CLOSED</bug_status>
          <resolution>DUPLICATE</resolution>
          <dup_id>3049</dup_id>
          
          
          
          <priority>P3</priority>
          <bug_severity>bug</bug_severity>
          <target_milestone>Future</target_milestone>
          
          
          
          <everconfirmed>1</everconfirmed>
          <reporter name="Ana Ribas Roca">ana.ribas@upcnet.es</reporter>
          <assigned_to name="Ken Murchison">murch@andrew.cmu.edu</assigned_to>
          <cc>brong@fastmail.fm</cc>
          <qa_contact name="The Cyrus Bugzilla List">cyrus-bugzilla@lists.andrew.cmu.edu</qa_contact>

      

      

      
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Ana Ribas Roca">ana.ribas@upcnet.es</who>
            <bug_when>2011-03-09 07:33:31 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Due to an accidental mistake of a user we have found a bug:

We have configured in our Sendmail one redirection from address1 to address2
When the message arrives to address2 (Cyrus), it is redirects again to address1 because the user has a sieve forward filter
Then begins a loop which Cyrus breaks the second time the message arrives to address2 for the use of duplicate delivery suppresion.

The message finally is not delivered and the sender is not notified about. This is a serious error!
I know this not happen very often but I think it is a bug that is necessary to solve

Is possible deliver the message if the duplicate is caused by a redirection and not by the vacation filter?
If the message cannot be delivered to destination then the sender should be informed.

Thanks a lot,


This is a similar bug that you have reported:
Bug 3049 - Sieve forwarding loop destroys e-mail</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Bron Gondwana">brong@fastmail.fm</who>
            <bug_when>2011-03-16 06:31:34 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Where would you have the message actually end up?  The user at address2 configured a forward rule with no associated fileinto rule, meaning they don&apos;t want it delivered into their mailbox, and your sendmail redirection sends it right back.

It sounds to me like the correct response for Cyrus on seeing the message a second time would actually be to bounce it &quot;delivery loop detected&quot; rather than
delivering it to the user.

Bron.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Bron Gondwana">brong@fastmail.fm</who>
            <bug_when>2011-07-03 17:26:15 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>I will merge this back to 3049, and update more on that bug.

*** This bug has been marked as a duplicate of bug 3049 ***</thetext>
          </long_desc>
      
      

    </bug>

</bugzilla>