<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes" ?>
<!DOCTYPE bugzilla SYSTEM "https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/bugzilla.dtd">

<bugzilla version="3.2.5.1-2"
          urlbase="https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/"
          maintainer="Dave McMurtrie &lt;dave64@andrew.cmu.edu&gt;"
>

    <bug>
          <bug_id>3504</bug_id>
          
          <creation_ts>2011-08-08 09:02 EDT</creation_ts>
          <short_desc>RFC 4422 ambiguity(?)</short_desc>
          <delta_ts>2011-08-08 09:05:14 EDT</delta_ts>
          <reporter_accessible>1</reporter_accessible>
          <cclist_accessible>1</cclist_accessible>
          <classification_id>1</classification_id>
          <classification>Unclassified</classification>
          <product>Cyrus SASL</product>
          <component>SASL</component>
          <version>2.1.x</version>
          <rep_platform>PC</rep_platform>
          <op_sys>Linux</op_sys>
          <bug_status>NEW</bug_status>
          
          
          
          
          
          <priority>P3</priority>
          <bug_severity>bug</bug_severity>
          <target_milestone>Future</target_milestone>
          
          
          
          <everconfirmed>1</everconfirmed>
          <reporter name="Jeroen van Meeuwen (Kolab Systems)">vanmeeuwen@kolabsys.com</reporter>
          <assigned_to name="Ken Murchison">murch@andrew.cmu.edu</assigned_to>
          <cc>thomas.b.edgar@gmail.com</cc>
          <qa_contact name="The Cyrus Bugzilla List">cyrus-bugzilla@lists.andrew.cmu.edu</qa_contact>

      

      

      
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Jeroen van Meeuwen (Kolab Systems)">vanmeeuwen@kolabsys.com</who>
            <bug_when>2011-08-08 09:02:45 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Section 3.6 of RFC 4422 [1] states:

&quot;&quot;&quot;
   At the conclusion of the authentication exchange, the server sends a
   message, the particulars of which are protocol specific, to the
   client indicating the outcome of the exchange.

   The outcome is not successful if

      -  the authentication exchange failed for any reason,

      -  the client&apos;s credentials could not be verified,

      -  the server cannot associate an identity with the client&apos;s
         credentials,

      -  the client-provided authorization identity string is malformed,

      -  the identity associated with the client&apos;s credentials is not
         authorized to act as the requested authorization identity,

      -  the negotiated security layer (or lack thereof) is not
         suitable, or

      -  the server is not willing to provide service to the client for
         any reason.

   The protocol may include an optional additional data field in this
   outcome message.  This field can only include additional data when
   the outcome is successful.

   If the outcome is successful and a security layer was negotiated,
   this layer is then installed.  If the outcome is unsuccessful, or a
   security layer was not negotiated, any existing security is left in
   place.

   The outcome message provided by the server can provide a way for the
   client to distinguish between errors that are best dealt with by re-
   prompting the user for her credentials, errors that are best dealt
   with by telling the user to try again later, and errors where the
   user must contact a system administrator for resolution (see the SYS
   and AUTH POP Response Codes [RFC3206] specification for an example).
   This distinction is particularly useful during scheduled server
   maintenance periods as it reduces support costs.  It is also
   important that the server can be configured such that the outcome
   message will not distinguish between a valid user with invalid
   credentials and an invalid user.
&quot;&quot;&quot;

I read this to say, that additional information in the SASL response can only be provided when the authentication is successful, but the last paragraph describes a scenario in which the client application can decide upon proper action using an error message as the additional information.

I read this to be ambiguous, in that additional information can only be included with successful authentication requests, but is useful only with authentication requests that are not successful.

I&apos;m looking to get this segment of the RFC clarified, and would appreciate your feedback, for a scenario in which Cyrus SASL uses the auth_httpform module to connect to an authentication and authorization service that applies a variety of business rules before allowing or denying the authentication request.

It would be most beneficial if the client application were able to somehow reproduce, visible to the user, the reason or any additional information an authentication request might not succeed. Ideally, the original message could be reproduced. However, I think that implies that the additional information is passed along the entire stack (from auth_httpform output to the Cyrus SASL output to the client application -Cyrus IMAP in this case-, all the way through to the client application -web interface + additional smart clients).

In order for that to happen, I think the following may be required;

- the ambiguity in the RFC -should you agree it exists- should be resolved and clarified,

- the Cyrus SASL code be made to allow passing along the original request result code / additional information field,

- the Cyrus IMAP code be made to allow passing along said additional information to the IMAP client.

[1] http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4422#section-3.6</thetext>
          </long_desc>
      
      

    </bug>

</bugzilla>