<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes" ?>
<!DOCTYPE bugzilla SYSTEM "https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/bugzilla.dtd">

<bugzilla version="3.2.5.1-2"
          urlbase="https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/"
          maintainer="Dave McMurtrie &lt;dave64@andrew.cmu.edu&gt;"
>

    <bug>
          <bug_id>3701</bug_id>
          
          <creation_ts>2012-05-18 05:08 EDT</creation_ts>
          <short_desc>Reliable backup/restore system for Cyrus</short_desc>
          <delta_ts>2016-06-20 01:47:14 EDT</delta_ts>
          <reporter_accessible>1</reporter_accessible>
          <cclist_accessible>1</cclist_accessible>
          <classification_id>1</classification_id>
          <classification>Unclassified</classification>
          <product>Cyrus IMAP</product>
          <component>IMAP</component>
          <version>2.5.x (next)</version>
          <rep_platform>PC</rep_platform>
          <op_sys>Linux</op_sys>
          <bug_status>ASSIGNED</bug_status>
          
          
          
          
          
          <priority>P3</priority>
          <bug_severity>bug</bug_severity>
          <target_milestone>2.5-next</target_milestone>
          
          <blocked>3674</blocked>
          
          <everconfirmed>1</everconfirmed>
          <reporter name="Bron Gondwana">brong@fastmail.fm</reporter>
          <assigned_to name="Bron Gondwana">brong@fastmail.fm</assigned_to>
          <cc>ellie@fastmail.com</cc>
          <qa_contact name="The Cyrus Bugzilla List">cyrus-bugzilla@lists.andrew.cmu.edu</qa_contact>

      

      

      
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Bron Gondwana">brong@fastmail.fm</who>
            <bug_when>2012-05-18 05:08:17 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>This is a placeholder ticket for building a backup and restore system using the replication protocol to reliably back up either a single mailbox or an entire user, both full and incremental backups.

Incremental backups will use the HIGHESTMODSEQ and LAST_UID fields to determine what is new.

Duplicate messages by GUID should not cause a second copy to be added to an incremental backup.

The tool must also have a &apos;verify&apos; mode, which can check that all messages files are present in the backup, and that incremental backups apply correctly on top of the old backup.

Ideally, the tool will be able to rename a user (or mailbox) and restore them to a different partition.

The tool must be able to back up ALL data stored in Cyrus, including sieve scripts, annotations and quota information.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Bron Gondwana">brong@fastmail.fm</who>
            <bug_when>2012-12-21 14:35:07 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>I did some great work with David Carter the other day in Cambridge for this - breaking down the exact list of data that&apos;s required to:

a) keep all RFC required features working
b) keep all Cyrus additional metadata correct

Now that we support metadata and annotations, we can shove any Cyrus specific stuff in there (where it&apos;s available read-only anyway, usually) and be all standards-happy.

We&apos;re not defining a compressed binary format - we&apos;re defining something which looks remarkably like IMAP-on-the-wire.

There are some internal format changes required first though!  I&apos;ll start there.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
      
      

    </bug>

</bugzilla>