<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes" ?>
<!DOCTYPE bugzilla SYSTEM "https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/bugzilla.dtd">

<bugzilla version="3.2.5.1-2"
          urlbase="https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/"
          maintainer="Dave McMurtrie &lt;dave64@andrew.cmu.edu&gt;"
>

    <bug>
          <bug_id>3721</bug_id>
          
          <creation_ts>2012-07-24 03:44 EDT</creation_ts>
          <short_desc>default admin enforced sieve script independent of user script</short_desc>
          <delta_ts>2013-09-18 17:05:09 EDT</delta_ts>
          <reporter_accessible>1</reporter_accessible>
          <cclist_accessible>1</cclist_accessible>
          <classification_id>1</classification_id>
          <classification>Unclassified</classification>
          <product>Cyrus IMAP</product>
          <component>Sieve</component>
          <version>2.5.x (next)</version>
          <rep_platform>All</rep_platform>
          <op_sys>All</op_sys>
          <bug_status>NEW</bug_status>
          
          
          
          
          
          <priority>P5</priority>
          <bug_severity>enhancement</bug_severity>
          <target_milestone>Future</target_milestone>
          
          
          
          <everconfirmed>1</everconfirmed>
          <reporter>costinel@gmail.com</reporter>
          <assigned_to name="Bron Gondwana">brong@fastmail.fm</assigned_to>
          <cc>awilliam@whitemice.org</cc>
    
    <cc>fedoraproject@cyberpear.com</cc>
    
    <cc>Leena.Heino@uta.fi</cc>
          <qa_contact name="The Cyrus Bugzilla List">cyrus-bugzilla@lists.andrew.cmu.edu</qa_contact>

      

      

      
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="">costinel@gmail.com</who>
            <bug_when>2012-07-24 03:44:42 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Hi,
I&apos;m not sure if, or for how long is the dev team aware of this requested feature.
I initially wrote to cyrus-devel mailing list where it has been criticized that there is no bug reported, so here it is.

I&apos;m copy pasting the discussion below.

I would appreciate your point of view regarding the subject.
Many thanks.

Date: Mon, 23 Jul 2012 23:26:53 +0300
Delivered-To: mailinglists35@gmail.com
Message-ID: &lt;CABjXrGFiD7A5-uR5g2K53eHTO+-eALNUdf4Co9Nybm7TP=bp5A@mail.gmail.com&gt;
Subject: official dev team position regarding multiple times requested feature
 (global sieve)
From: mailing list subscriber &lt;mailinglists35@gmail.com&gt;
To: cyrus-devel@lists.andrew.cmu.edu

Hi,

There are many situations where users are hardly able to figure out
what to do if a shortcut icon has dissapeared from their desktop.
Among their email needs, two features stand out: ability to view the
possible spam emails into a separate folder and ability to setup their
own &quot;out of office&quot; messages.

The first one has multiple solutions but each involve additional work
from the sysadmin: either scripting or writing documentation to
instruct users enable the feature on their own.
The second one is handled either by client-side user script editing or
a web interface.
For a tech-savy user, combining the two is not a big challenge,
however our typical joe is going to eventually quit reading
instructions shortly at beginning and blame the IT for poor support.

On the other side, there is the management who is unable to understand
why the out of office and spam filtering must cost dollars per user (=
ms exchange) just to have these features usable by all employees.

The poor IT guy sits between these two forces and then pursues
developers of free software for this and that feature.

With above figure in mind, I&apos;m looking at the history of request for
ability to have a forced, default, site-wide sieve script that the
user or any other sieve client is unable to alter (I&apos;ll just pick most
relevant):

2004, with reference to 2001:
http://goo.gl/Gbo0k

2006: A submitted patch
http://www.irbs.net/internet/info-cyrus/0612/0231.html

2007: A very good synthesis:
http://goo.gl/Lo33b

2010: sieve include implemented in v.2.3.0, still fails to meet above
requirements

With all due respect, what is the development&apos;s team position
regarding this feature and how do the development team see a solution
that meets both requirements?

Thank you.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="">costinel@gmail.com</who>
            <bug_when>2012-07-24 06:45:50 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>&gt; 2004, with reference to 2001:
&gt; http://goo.gl/Gbo0k

digging further, the 2001 message mentions another patch without link, found it
here:
http://www.mail-archive.com/info-cyrus@lists.andrew.cmu.edu/msg04406.html</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Bron Gondwana">brong@fastmail.fm</who>
            <bug_when>2012-10-19 14:32:42 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Per the discussion on the mailing list, this is not P1, and it&apos;s not slated for inclusion in 2.5.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="">costinel@gmail.com</who>
            <bug_when>2012-11-07 04:33:43 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>http://lists.andrew.cmu.edu/pipermail/cyrus-devel/2012-October/002691.html

On Thu, Sep 20, 2012 at 3:26 PM, Bron Gondwana &lt;brong at fastmail.fm&gt; wrote:
&gt; Roughly:
&gt;
&gt; a) nobody else wants to do it.
&gt; b) if you write a patch (or get someone to) and it doesn&apos;t break other
&gt;    stuff or cause massive maintenance headaches or backwards compatibility
&gt;    problems, we&apos;ll include it.
&gt; c) you can do whatever you want with your own copy of course.
&gt;
&gt; Bron ( or as they say in the parlance: patches welcome )

Hi,
Does this patch qualify for b) ?
http://lists.andrew.cmu.edu/pipermail/cyrus-devel/2006-December/000227.html
Thanks.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
      
      

    </bug>

</bugzilla>