<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes" ?>
<!DOCTYPE bugzilla SYSTEM "https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/bugzilla.dtd">

<bugzilla version="3.2.5.1-2"
          urlbase="https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/"
          maintainer="Dave McMurtrie &lt;dave64@andrew.cmu.edu&gt;"
>

    <bug>
          <bug_id>3805</bug_id>
          
          <creation_ts>2013-08-08 05:52 EDT</creation_ts>
          <short_desc>Enterprise email set up unknowingly</short_desc>
          <delta_ts>2013-08-08 06:34:57 EDT</delta_ts>
          <reporter_accessible>1</reporter_accessible>
          <cclist_accessible>1</cclist_accessible>
          <classification_id>1</classification_id>
          <classification>Unclassified</classification>
          <product>Cyrus IMAP</product>
          <component>lib</component>
          <version>2.5.x (next)</version>
          <rep_platform>Macintosh</rep_platform>
          <op_sys>Mac OS X</op_sys>
          <bug_status>CLOSED</bug_status>
          <resolution>INVALID</resolution>
          
          
          
          
          <priority>P3</priority>
          <bug_severity>bug</bug_severity>
          <target_milestone>Future</target_milestone>
          
          
          
          <everconfirmed>1</everconfirmed>
          <reporter name="Greg Nafziger">nafpropertyman@icloud.com</reporter>
          <assigned_to name="Bron Gondwana">brong@fastmail.fm</assigned_to>
          
          <qa_contact name="The Cyrus Bugzilla List">cyrus-bugzilla@lists.andrew.cmu.edu</qa_contact>

      

      

      
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Greg Nafziger">nafpropertyman@icloud.com</who>
            <bug_when>2013-08-08 05:52:58 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Very long story short. I have been dealing with what appears to be a multitude of development platforms dropped on me by my ex when she lived with me. I have went through two iphone 4s, a macbook and now two hard drives on a macbook pro. I found information that I was connecting to a cyrus server and my computer appears to be running a bash/bin shell. Im sorry man I&apos;m not a programmer but my life has been ruined by this. With an enterprise platform set up, you ate able to control the devices correct? Because no matter what I seem to be the client on my own devices and she definitely changed my hotmail to an exchang email....I could live with it all if she also wasn&apos;t usin an 8 month baby boy Ive only seen 120 hours in his entire life. The only thing that ever worked to stop the Voice Over control was resetting my iPhone and the only advice she ver gave me other than that I was crazy and she knew nothing about it was.....&quot;I think you should stop resetting your iPhone!&quot; No shit....


there is Perl 5.10 and 5.12 and well just a whole platform of horrible things if you dis not put them there. Sorry to bother you. Its been a year of hell</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Bron Gondwana">brong@fastmail.fm</who>
            <bug_when>2013-08-08 06:34:57 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Hi,

Sounds like you&apos;ve had a rough time.

I&apos;m afraid I can&apos;t help you much, other than to assure you that the Cyrus server is just an email storage server - it doesn&apos;t do anything else.  It used to ship with early versions of Mac OS, though I believe they&apos;ve switched to another system called Dovecot now.

We are not able to control any of your devices.  We don&apos;t have access to any of your computers.  If anything is happening on your systems, it won&apos;t be due to Cyrus.

Regards,

Bron.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
      
      

    </bug>

</bugzilla>