<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes" ?>
<!DOCTYPE bugzilla SYSTEM "https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/bugzilla.dtd">

<bugzilla version="3.2.5.1-2"
          urlbase="https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/"
          maintainer="Dave McMurtrie &lt;dave64@andrew.cmu.edu&gt;"
>

    <bug>
          <bug_id>3865</bug_id>
          
          <creation_ts>2014-09-23 14:37 EDT</creation_ts>
          <short_desc>Support non-ASCII UTF-8 email addresses and header (RFC 6530, RFC 6855)</short_desc>
          <delta_ts>2014-09-23 14:37:47 EDT</delta_ts>
          <reporter_accessible>1</reporter_accessible>
          <cclist_accessible>1</cclist_accessible>
          <classification_id>1</classification_id>
          <classification>Unclassified</classification>
          <product>Cyrus IMAP</product>
          <component>LMTP</component>
          <version>2.4.17</version>
          <rep_platform>All</rep_platform>
          <op_sys>All</op_sys>
          <bug_status>NEW</bug_status>
          
          
          
          
          
          <priority>P3</priority>
          <bug_severity>enhancement</bug_severity>
          <target_milestone>2.5-next</target_milestone>
          
          
          
          <everconfirmed>1</everconfirmed>
          <reporter name="Mark Martinec">Mark.Martinec+cyrus@ijs.si</reporter>
          <assigned_to name="Bron Gondwana">brong@fastmail.fm</assigned_to>
          <cc>Mark.Martinec+cyrus@ijs.si</cc>
          <qa_contact name="The Cyrus Bugzilla List">cyrus-bugzilla@lists.andrew.cmu.edu</qa_contact>

      

      

      
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Mark Martinec">Mark.Martinec+cyrus@ijs.si</who>
            <bug_when>2014-09-23 14:37:47 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Now that unfortunate RFC 4952 and RFC 5504 have been abandoned
and replaced by a more viable approach in February 2012:

  RFC 6530: Overview and Framework for Internationalized Email
  RFC 6531: SMTP Extension for Internationalized Email
  RFC 6532: Internationalized Email Headers

and the IMAP/POP3 counterparts in March 2013:

  RFC 6855: IMAP Support for UTF-8
  RFC 6856: Post Office Protocol Version 3 (POP3) Support for UTF-8

  RFC 6857: Post-Delivery Message Downgrading for Internationalized
            Email Messages
  RFC 6858: Simplified POP and IMAP Downgrading for Internationalized Email

... then considering that the support for Internationalized Email
has been made available:

- in Postfix MTA since 2014-07-15 (targeted for stable release 2.12);

- on 2014-08-05 Google announced that Gmail will recognize addresses
  that contain accented or non-Latin characters, with more support
  for internationalization to follow.

- gmail.com mailers are announcing support for SMTP Extension for
  Internationalized Email (SMTPUTF8);

- amavisd-new content filter supports it since version 2.10.0 (2014-09)

- support in sendmail and Dovecot is murmured to be in works.



IT SEEMS THE MISSING LINK IN THE CHAIN IS NOW THE CYRUS IMAP SERVER.



Cyrus LMTP server should:

- announce service extension &quot;Internationalized Email&quot; (SMTPUTF8)
  in its LHLO response (RFC 6531);

- accept paramater SMTPUTF8 in a received MAIL FROM command;

- accept non-ASCII UTF-8 sender and recipient e-mail addresses
  if allowed by the SMTPUTF8 parameter in MAIL FROM command;

- accept non-ASCII UTF-8 characters in a mail header section
  (RFC 6532) (i.e. in header field bodies, not in header field names)
  if requested by the SMTPUTF8 parameter in MAIL FROM command;

- just not be picky about non-ASCII UTF-8 in IMAP/POP3.


Btw, currently Cyrus LMTP server responds with:
  501 5.5.4 Syntax error in parameters
if it sees an UTF-8 sender or recipient e-mail address.


Here are some interesting notes from:
  http://rant.gulbrandsen.priv.no/eai-implementation-notes
shedding some fears about changes required for IMAP and POP3:

  6855 is for IMAP; it&apos;s great. Like 6531, it simply lets you use
    UTF8 in most contexts where you expect to. There&apos;s very little
    optional about it, and the mandatory parts are fairly easy to
    implement.

  6856 is for POP3; it&apos;s also great, for the same reasons as 6855:
    There&apos;s just one way to implement it, and that one way lacks
    unnecessary complications.

  6857 is the ambitious way to present unicode mail to unextended
    IMAP/POP clients. Mail is stored using unicode and converted
    (as far as possible) to legacy syntax at read time.

  6858 is the simple way to present unicode mail to unextended
    IMAP/POP clients. I wrote that, because I thought 6857-in-spe
    was too much work and offered too many opportunities for error.
    In my opinion 6858 is much simpler and delivers results in the
    same class as 6857: Much better than nothing, but not perfect.
    Both are good enough to read the mail, neither is good enough
    to reply.

  IETF working groups don&apos;t often define two RFCs for the same task.
  In this case, the general feeling was that one size did not fit
  all, and that having two specifications was the best way to cater
  to everyone&apos;s taste.

  IMAP/POP server implementers should implement either 6857 or 6858,
  depending on how much effort they want to put into it.

Some more potentially useful links:
  https://github.com/arnt/eai-test-messages
  http://rant.gulbrandsen.priv.no/eai-autoresponder



It would be a pity having to wait and clamor for another four years
till the Cyrus 2.6 to eventually support internationalized mail,
considering the internationalized mail has finally caught some traction.
Please help break the chicken-and-egg problem!</thetext>
          </long_desc>
      
      

    </bug>

</bugzilla>