<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes" ?>
<!DOCTYPE bugzilla SYSTEM "https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/bugzilla.dtd">

<bugzilla version="3.2.5.1-2"
          urlbase="https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/"
          maintainer="Dave McMurtrie &lt;dave64@andrew.cmu.edu&gt;"
>

    <bug>
          <bug_id>3869</bug_id>
          
          <creation_ts>2014-10-30 09:01 EDT</creation_ts>
          <short_desc>Replication breaks if a mailbox has expire annotations on folders</short_desc>
          <delta_ts>2015-02-04 13:03:24 EDT</delta_ts>
          <reporter_accessible>1</reporter_accessible>
          <cclist_accessible>1</cclist_accessible>
          <classification_id>1</classification_id>
          <classification>Unclassified</classification>
          <product>Cyrus IMAP</product>
          <component>IMAP</component>
          <version>2.4.x (next)</version>
          <rep_platform>PC</rep_platform>
          <op_sys>Linux</op_sys>
          <bug_status>NEW</bug_status>
          
          
          
          
          
          <priority>P3</priority>
          <bug_severity>bug</bug_severity>
          <target_milestone>Future</target_milestone>
          
          
          
          <everconfirmed>1</everconfirmed>
          <reporter name="Alan Robertson">alanjrobertson@gmail.com</reporter>
          <assigned_to name="Bron Gondwana">brong@fastmail.fm</assigned_to>
          
          <qa_contact name="The Cyrus Bugzilla List">cyrus-bugzilla@lists.andrew.cmu.edu</qa_contact>

      

      

      
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Alan Robertson">alanjrobertson@gmail.com</who>
            <bug_when>2014-10-30 09:01:23 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Cyrus IMAP 2.4.17 on x64. Not murder configuration, stand alone system replicating to another.

virtdomains: userid
unixhierarchysep: on
altnamespace: on

Multiple partitions. 

I can freely move user accounts between partitions until I set an expire Annotation on part of the mailbox. The mailbox moves on the master but not on the slave. The Masters sync_client bails with the message:

 ANNOTATION Error in do_sync(): bailing out! Bad protocol

Removing the &quot;ANNOTATION&quot; lines from the log allows that log to be processed.

With some testing it looks like the expire Annotation makes it to the failover mailstore correctly when it is set and clear from the sync log. Running the rename to move the account appears to add in another ANNOTATION entry into the sync log and the sync_client daemon exits as above.

After it has failed to move on the slave, with the failed sync log rerun (with the ANNOTATION line removed) any subsequent partition moves appear to work correctly.

Have seen this behaviour on 4 separate master/slave systems. All running CentOS6 x64</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Alan Robertson">alanjrobertson@gmail.com</who>
            <bug_when>2015-02-04 13:03:24 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Additional to what I&apos;ve said I have just noticed that post-rename and partition move on the MASTER node the moved mailbox ends up with no expire annotations at all. They just vanish. 

Checked this happens on two different 2.4.17 systems, one CentOS6 x64 and another CentOS5 x86. Interestingly on the x86 system rolling sync_client carries on working and successfully completes the rename on the master and slave - albeit with the expire annotations vanishing from the MASTER side. On the x64 sync_client bails and the expire annotations also disappear.</thetext>
          </long_desc>
      
      

    </bug>

</bugzilla>