<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes" ?>
<!DOCTYPE bugzilla SYSTEM "https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/bugzilla.dtd">

<bugzilla version="3.2.5.1-2"
          urlbase="https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/"
          maintainer="Dave McMurtrie &lt;dave64@andrew.cmu.edu&gt;"
>

    <bug>
          <bug_id>3879</bug_id>
          
          <creation_ts>2014-12-29 04:46 EDT</creation_ts>
          <short_desc>[PATCH] Access to multiple accounts to the same server from the same client fails with &quot;403 Forbidden&quot;</short_desc>
          <delta_ts>2015-02-02 02:26:22 EDT</delta_ts>
          <reporter_accessible>1</reporter_accessible>
          <cclist_accessible>1</cclist_accessible>
          <classification_id>1</classification_id>
          <classification>Unclassified</classification>
          <product>Cyrus IMAP</product>
          <component>CalDAV</component>
          <version>2.4.17</version>
          <rep_platform>PC</rep_platform>
          <op_sys>Linux</op_sys>
          <bug_status>CLOSED</bug_status>
          <resolution>INVALID</resolution>
          
          
          
          
          <priority>P3</priority>
          <bug_severity>bug</bug_severity>
          <target_milestone>Future</target_milestone>
          
          
          
          <everconfirmed>1</everconfirmed>
          <reporter name="Daniel Dickinson">cyrus-bugs@daniel.thecshore.com</reporter>
          <assigned_to name="Ken Murchison">murch@andrew.cmu.edu</assigned_to>
          
          <qa_contact name="The Cyrus Bugzilla List">cyrus-bugzilla@lists.andrew.cmu.edu</qa_contact>

      

      

      
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Daniel Dickinson">cyrus-bugs@daniel.thecshore.com</who>
            <bug_when>2014-12-29 04:46:41 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>Due to strict interpretation/implementation of RFC for HTTP Auth, HTTP Auth is not re-requested for different URIs only for different server names.  This causes access to multiple cyrus calendars from the same client instance (e.g. same Thunderbird Lightning profile) to fail unless you modify the ACLs to allow access to all desired calendars by a single user account (in addition the owner).

The following hack addresses this by rerequesting HTTP Auth if the httpd userid does not match the calendar URI userid.

Not that Mozilla Thunderbird has gone through some angst wrt to this issue and introduced and about:config option calendars.network.multirealm to handle this case.

Also apparently iCal does something like this by default (that is treats different calendars as requiring different authentication even though the server name is the same).</thetext>
          </long_desc>
          <long_desc isprivate="0">
            <who name="Daniel Dickinson">cyrus-bugs@daniel.thecshore.com</who>
            <bug_when>2015-02-02 02:26:22 EDT</bug_when>
            <thetext>This bug is another that was actually the result of virtual domains not being supported by caldav/carddav server.  Once the virtual domain support was correctly implemented (the final working patch which I will attach the virtual domain bug report momentarily).</thetext>
          </long_desc>
      
      

    </bug>

</bugzilla>